<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0'
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Red Starfish's Webpage</title>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <link>https://redstarfish.github.io/blog.html</link>
    <description>My articles and blog posts</description>
    <atom:link href="https://redstarfish.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

    <item>
      <title>From LXDE To Openbox Then Back To LXDE/Openbox</title>
      <link>https://redstarfish.github.io/blog/from-lxde-openbox-lxde.html</link>
      <guid>https://redstarfish.github.io/blog/from-lxde-openbox-lxde.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, Sep 29, 2020 10:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[
      <h2>From LXDE To Openbox Then Back To LXDE/Openbox </h2>
      <h3>Author: Red Starfish</h3>
      <h4>Date: 29th September, 2020</h4>

      <img src="/pix/lxde-icon.png" style="max-width: 50%;margin: auto; display: block;" alt="LXDE Icon" title="LXDE-Icon">
      <div class="blog">

      <h3 id="intro">First Interactions with LXDE</h3>
      
      <p>
      My first experience
      with <a href="https://www.lxde.org/">LXDE</a> (By default
      LXDE uses Openbox but you don't get the right click menu,
      autostart or enviroment that defines openbox) came with
      <a href="https://trisquel.info">Trisquel Mini</a>. I wanted
      to use Trisquel(8) and it came with two editions MATE and
      LXDE. I saw no point in installing Trisquel using a larger
      ISO when I was going to customize it, use my own choice of
      applications and not going to use the default ones provided
      as default by Trisquel. Also I knew that what desktop
      enviroment comes pre-installed doesn't matter because I can
      always install the one I want, later.
      </p>
      <p>
      So, I went with LXDE edition, thinking that I'd install XFCE
      later after installation. But when using XFCE, I kept coming
      back to LXDE (with Trisquel theme) mainly because it was
      lightweight and felt snappier. I also changed some
      keybindings to suit my needs. But few things I liked (and
      still like) from XFCE were:
      <ul>
      <li>xfce4-appfinder</li>
      <li>xfce4-notifyd</li>
      <li>xfce4-pulseaudio-plugin - <em>Really useful</em></li>
      <li>xfce4-screenshooter</li>
      </ul>
      
      So while using LXDE (trisquel themed), I was using used some
      components from xfce4 too.
      </p>
      
      <p>
      After few months as Trisquel 8 was getting really old, I
      decided to move to <a href="https://parabola.nu">Parabola
      GNU/Linux-libre</a> (Note: If you want to use Trisquel, you
      should install Trisquel 9). Here my first instinct again was
      to install LXDE, but after installation I didn't like it. So
      I immediately installed xfce4 again. I was really surprised
      how much progress it had gone through in the last 3-4
      years. But I became increasingly frustrated as my preferred
      keybindings (which I created while using Trisquel) were not
      there, so I started using LXDE again with above mentioned
      xfce4 programs.
      </p>

      <h3 id="openbox">From LXDE To Openbox</h3>
      <p>
      While above mentioned things were happening, I tried using
      the vanilla Openbox few times, but as it's so minimalist and
      I didn't know what additional softwares to use, I exited
      Openbox within 5 minutes everytime logged into a
      openbox-session.
      </p>
      <p>
      Then I found this really great
      <a href="https://fedoramagazine.org/openbox-fedora/">Fedora
      Magazine article</a>. This helped me a lot to move towards
      using Openbox. Openbox session became usable to me.
      </p>
      <p>
      One thing I noticed, standalone LXDE programs were making
      openbox more complete but few things weren't working out for
      me in Openbox, for example:
      <ul>
      <li>Screen wasn't locking immediately after I closed the
      Laptop lid.</li>
      <li>
      No Trash support.
      </li>
      <li>
      External drive wasn't mounting automatically, I needed to
      use CLI and become root to work with external drive. Even
      root couldn't change the permissions or ownership of the
      files in the external drives.
      </li>
      </ul>

      So these things kept bugging me. On one hand, I wanted to go
      back to LXDE and on the other, I liked the tint2 panel
      instead of lxpanel, I wanted the right click menu of
      openbox, nitrogen for setting wallpapers etc.
      </p>
      <h3 id="lxde-openbox">Using LXDE/Openbox</h3>
      <p>
      I decided to go back to LXDE (lxsession) but with a twist. 
      </p>
      <p>
      To use my preferred panel and get back the Openbox's right
      click menu, I found that these things are being controlled
      by LXDE's autostart file. This file is located at
      <code>
      /home/user/.config/lxsession/LXDE/autostart
      </code>.  Once I got to this file, stripping things were
      very easy. LXDE's right click and wallpaper is controlled by
      pcmanfm in desktop mode. I changed it to daemon mode. That
      way I got back Openbox's right click menu.
      </p>
      
      <p>
      I removed the lxpanel and replaced with tint2. This way, I
      could use tint2 in LXDE instead having to lxpanel.
      </p>

      <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
      <p>
      So, this is the long tale of how I've found the desktop the
      way I want. Which is the full functionality of Openbox
      complemented by LXDE programs.
      </p>
      <img src="../pix/mydesktop.jpg" style="max-width: 50%;margin: auto; display: block;" alt="My Desktop" title="My Desktop">
      
      <h3 id="helping">Helping You</h3>
      <p>
      If you want to have your desktop just like I have. Do the
      following:
      <ul>
      <li>
      Clone my Dotfiles repository. Here you'll find all
      the necessary configuration files.<br/>
      <code>$ git clone
      https://codeberg.org/Red_Starfish/My_Dotfiles.git</code>
      
      </li>
      <br/>
      <li>
      In the openbox directory, you'll find the following files:
      <ol>
      <li>lxde-rc.xml - Put it in
      <code>~/.config/openbox/lxde-rc.xml</code></li>
      <li>menu.xml - Put it in <code>~/.config/openbox/menu.xml</code></li>
      <li>autostart - Put it in
      <code>~/.config/lxsession/LXDE/autostart</code></li>
      <li>tint2rc - Put it
      in <code>~/.config/tint2/tint2rc</code> 
      <br/>
      (make sure you have tint2 installed though.)</li>
      </ol>
      </li>
      <br/>
      <li>You will find some awesome wallpapers from here:<br/>
      <code>
      $ git clone https://gitlab.com/dwt1/wallpapers.git
      </code>
      <br/><br/>You'll need something like nitrogen to set wallpapers.
      </li>
      <br/>
      <li>
      Next time you login, login to LXDE session.
      </li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      </div>
      ]]></description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Why I have Made This Website]]></title>
      <link>https://redstarfish.github.io/blog/why-i-made-this-website.html</link>
      <guid>https://redstarfish.github.io/blog/why-i-made-this-website.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, Sep 26, 2020 13:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[

<h2>Why I Have Made This Website</h2>

      <p>
	I think this post, telling you why I've made this website, would be
	most appropriate as the first post.
      </p>
      <p>
	As most of my fellow GNU users and free software enthusiasts agree
	that, the state of current internet is very poor. The internet and
	the World Wide Web(WWW) is controlled by the 5 corporations(GAFAM),
	but especially by the Google. As Google's chromium has monopoly in
	the browser market, whatever it is implementing, is becoming a "web
	standard". Also websites are very bloated nowadays. Many website
	lose functionality when you block javascript(and you should). They
	hardly works with text based browsers. We also don't see people
	having their own website like they used to have. Mostly they spend
	their time on Facebook and Twitter(and other such proprietary social
	medial platforms). The way Facebook/Twitter is using these people
	for their own gain is outrageous (to quote Richard Stallman:
	Facebook has no user, it has 'used'). They are even influencing
	elections.(By the way,
	fediverse/<a href="https://joinmastodon.org">Mastodon</a> are very
	good solutions to Facebook/Twitter)
      </p>
      <p>
	Few months ago I saw a youtube video from the youtuber known
	as <a href="https://lukesmith.xyz">Luke Smith</a>. He makes GNU,
	Linux and free software related videos. In that video he was telling
	how easy and important it is to have your own website. So from then
	on I had a desire to have my own website. Before that I used to
	think, having website is too hard and money consuming. But I had zero
	knowledge about managing websites. I knew some basic HTML and CSS,
	and that was all. Also as I was very busy at that time, I decided to
	let the matter drop.
      </p>
      <p>
	But yesterday, suddenly a thought came to me(an itch?). I had known
	about Github pages all along but never considered using it because I
	have serious problems with both Github and Microsoft(the company
	which owns it). Then I considered, while using Github pages I am not
	forcing people to use proprietary software. This whole site is made
	up of HTML and CSS. So having this website is not immoral, and I can
	totally have it. It'll also give me experience about how to make
	websites. Most importantly I have enough free time now to play with
	it. So yesterday evening, I started building this website.<br/>
	Previously I had some basic interaction with Git, then I read some
	posts about how to use Github pages, and realized, it was not that
	hard. I also had come across a site whose style sheet I liked. I
	copied it, made some minor modification and make it look red instead
	of purple(that website was under CC BY-SA), so here is the
	result. The fact that you can see the source of any website you
	visit is really helpful.
      </p>
      <p>
	I also wanted to have RSS feeds in my website. RSS feeds are a great
	way to follow websites without any 3rd party meddling and for that
	reason it is a must have for me. So I spend another half hour
	learning how to do it and I am really surprised by how easy it is to
	set up. I wish more websites would use it.
      </p>
      <p>
	I think this is enough for the first post, GNU Emacs tells me we
	have already crossed 600 words. And I don't want readers to lose
	attention midway while reading this.
      </p>
      <p>
	So, see you in the next post. If you want to get notified,
	don't forget to subscribe to this blog
	using <a href="../rss.xml">RSS feed</a>. Also do you have any
	comment regarding this post or website? See details in
	the <a href="../contact.html">contact page</a> on how to
	contact me.
      </p>

]]></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
